<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title><![CDATA[Best Monk]]></title><description><![CDATA[Best Monk]]></description><link>http://bestmonk.xyz</link><generator>metalsmith-feed</generator><lastBuildDate>Sat, 16 Apr 2016 11:39:35 GMT</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://bestmonk.xyz/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title><![CDATA[“Refocusing Each Spec Around Their Core Concepts”]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>I was originally going to give my opinion on each change, change isn&#39;t necessarily bad, I feel the weight of removals in comparison to additions speaks volumes without injecting my own opinion into things. For that reason, this post will <strong>only</strong> list changes.</p>
<h2 id="what-mistweaver-has-lost">What Mistweaver Has Lost</h2>
<ul>
<li>Eminence, a method of doing damage and healing at the same time. Along with the position-based gameplay of statue and player placement.</li>
<li>Crane Stance, along with accompanying buffs such as Tiger Strikes and Vital Mists.</li>
<li>Mana Tea, removing a significant amount of proactive gameplay.</li>
<li>Chi, killing any remnants of proactive gameplay.</li>
<li>Zen Meditation, a method of &quot;soaking&quot; exceptionally hard hitting abilities in raids.</li>
<li>The ability to &quot;soak&quot; magic damage with Diffuse Magic.</li>
<li>Fortifying Brew, a standard baseline defensive cooldown.</li>
<li>Gift of the Serpent.</li>
<li>Vital Mists and Tiger Power, two powerful melee buffs to track.</li>
<li>Spinning Crane Kick.</li>
<li>Uplift, and the interaction it had with Renewing Mist.</li>
<li>Jade Mists.</li>
<li>Detonate Chi.</li>
<li>Touch of Death.</li>
<li>Spear Hand Strike.</li>
<li>Nimble Brew.</li>
<li>Expel Harm.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="what-mistweaver-has-gained">What Mistweaver Has Gained</h2>
<ul>
<li>Gust of Mist.</li>
<li>Vivify.</li>
<li>Essence Font.</li>
<li>Sheilun&#39;s Gift.</li>
</ul>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>What you’re seeing in Legion falls under one of two different goals:</p>
<p>-Refocusing each spec around their core concepts</p>
<p>-Reduced reliance on cooldowns, both offensive and defensive</p>
</blockquote>
<p><a href="http://blue.mmo-champion.com/topic/408573-on-pruning-pvp-and-our-goals-for-legion/">Source</a></p>
]]></description><link>http://bestmonk.xyz/blog/refocusing-each-spec-around-their-core-concepts</link><guid isPermaLink="true">http://bestmonk.xyz/blog/refocusing-each-spec-around-their-core-concepts</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Reglitch]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 16 Apr 2016 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Gust of Mists and Spell Selection]]></title><description><![CDATA[<h2 id="no-it-s-not-broken">No, It&#39;s Not Broken</h2>
<p>Yes, Gust of Mists does not effect Area of Effect healing, this does not mean that it is inherently broken. It creates a gearing strategy that removes Essence Font from your spell selection pool in a lot of situations. You do not necessarily lose healing from this omission though, as Gust of Mists is over-budgeted for a lot of spells.</p>
<h2 id="budget-comparison">Budget Comparison</h2>
<p>Take a look at rating conversion rates:</p>
<pre><code class="hljs"><span class="hljs-attribute">Haste</span>: <span class="hljs-string">275</span>
<span class="hljs-attribute">Crit</span>: <span class="hljs-string">300</span>
<span class="hljs-attribute">Mastery</span>: <span class="hljs-string">300</span>
<span class="hljs-attribute">Versatility</span>: <span class="hljs-string">350</span></code></pre>

<p>For your typical spells, this results in the following breakdown:</p>
<hr>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Stat [+300]</th>
<th>Renewing Mist</th>
<th>Effuse</th>
<th>Enveloping Mist</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Mastery</td>
<td>10% spellpower</td>
<td>10% spellpower</td>
<td>13% spellpower</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Crit</td>
<td>7.15% spellpower</td>
<td>2.2% spellpower</td>
<td>11.88% spellpower</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Haste</td>
<td>7.8% spellpower</td>
<td>0% spellpower</td>
<td>12.96% spellpower</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<hr>
<p>We&#39;ll only look at the 3 stats that are competitive output-wise here, versatility has it&#39;s own benefits but we won&#39;t derail this post.</p>
<p>You can quite clearly see that in all situations mastery has the upper hand - in fact, mastery would have the upper hand even if the amount of stats provided by haste or critical strike rating were slightly above it. Here&#39;s why;</p>
<ul>
<li>Gust of Mist is a direct heal, mastery allows you to &#39;withdraw&#39; prolonged healing from HoTs and get it when you need it.</li>
<li>Gust of Mists provides both efficiency and superior output, haste does not out-perform it at any point - yet with each point of haste you incur a cost penalty.</li>
</ul>
<p>In effect, Gust of Mists is crit but better - crit has always been an amazing statistic for Mistweavers, and it still will be because it synergizes well with Gust of Mists and doesn&#39;t increase mana expenditure.</p>
<h2 id="so-what-s-the-problem-">So What&#39;s the Problem?</h2>
<p>Earlier I mentioned that I don&#39;t see an optional phasing out of Essence Font as a problem. It&#39;s not; but there are situations where spells will be phased out in every possible situation, simply because Mastery and Effuse will overtake them.</p>
<p>In particular, the two largest culprits are:</p>
<div class="tooltip-spread two-items">
  <a class="wow-spell" data-id="197945"></a>
  <a class="wow-spell" data-id="205406"></a>
</div>

<p>In one case, the spell is a &quot;utility&quot; that heals players as you teleport them at the cost of your Transcendence ability. In the other, it is the hallmark artifact ability that is supposed to supplement the class, currently the assumption is being made that the current stack count max on alpha is a bug.</p>
<p>Both of these spells get easily outmatched by Gust of Mists on Effuse. Yet they both fit in the criteria for Gust of Mists&#39; beneficiaries, creating a situation where these spells simply won&#39;t be used. For example, why risk a volatile change in position for a smaller heal?</p>
<p>Mistwalk in particular can be used ~20% more often than Transcendence, but offers little in the way of the functionality that Transcendence has. Transcendence is an ability that is used to go places where players aren&#39;t at already, Mistwalk lacks that major use case and a tiny 350% heal does not bring it to standard - particularly when the opportunity cost of not taking either Chi Burst or Zen Pulse exists.</p>
<p>It is clear that Chi Torpedo served as a mobility/heal combination far better than Mistwalk ever will; as it let you heal the raid and move with them when necessary. For Mistwalk to serve the same purpose; you would have to wait in the same area players moved from to get the mobility benefit - arguably killing yourself in the process. Ultimately the ability feels like something that Holy Paladins would benefit more from.</p>
<p>Sheilun&#39;s Gift is a little more complex, if the current alpha behavior of stacking to 12 continues - then it will exist as a seldom used ability. It will still be used however, so it would exist in the same area as Essence Font in terms of being an ability that becomes less frequently selected, but when it is that selection is particularly in favor of the spell. If it does not stack beyond an easily attainable mastery value, the spell will simply be phased out completely.</p>
<p>So to conclude, Gust isn&#39;t a broken mastery in any sense of the term - it&#39;s simply unique in it&#39;s implementation. There are some potential problem areas where it can simply phase out other spells, and it would be nice to see these areas cleaned up. Especially in the case of Mistwalk, there is the problem of finding an actual use case for a heal and mobility combo that heals a single target and forces you to lag behind them. This simply doesn&#39;t happen in PvE, meaning the only realistic use for the ability is battlefield traversal; something we have next to no need of.</p>
]]></description><link>http://bestmonk.xyz/blog/gust-of-mists-and-spell-selection</link><guid isPermaLink="true">http://bestmonk.xyz/blog/gust-of-mists-and-spell-selection</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Reglitch]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 11 Apr 2016 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Mistweaver Design Space]]></title><description><![CDATA[<h2 id="a-utility-post-really-">A Utility Post? Really?</h2>
<p>No, not a utility post. Let&#39;s dispel once and for all with this fiction that I don&#39;t know what I&#39;m doing. I know EXACTLY what I&#39;m doing. I am undertaking a systematic effort to change this game, to make Mistweaver more like the rest of the healers. Joking aside, this post isn&#39;t looking strictly at utility, instead we&#39;re just looking at buttons that each specialization has that doesn&#39;t fall under typical healing spell selection. For some classes this gets a little blurred, but where that happens I&#39;ll make an argument as to why it falls outside that definition.</p>
<p>I firmly believe that there is a problem worth noting here, one that for reasons of ensuring variety and fun should be looked at.   This problem is that baseline abilities provide an anchor for which to augment the specialization through other avenues such as set bonuses, or artifact traits. Both of which look very boring for Mistweaver, I&#39;m not sure it&#39;s a coincidence.</p>
<p>In this post I will list each class&#39; spells, the criteria of which is as follows:</p>
<ul>
<li>Isn&#39;t typically used during regular spell selection, i.e. not a standard single target or AoE spell.</li>
<li>Isn&#39;t the specialization&#39;s standard raid cooldown.</li>
<li>Isn&#39;t the specialization&#39;s standard tank cooldown.</li>
<li>Is an ability that is unique and powerful.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="shaman">Shaman</h2>
<h3 id="base-spells">Base Spells</h3>
<h4 id="mobility">Mobility</h4>
<div class="tooltip-spread two-items">
  <a class="wow-spell" data-id="2645"></a>
  <a class="wow-spell" data-id="79206"></a>
</div>

<h4 id="raid-boons">Raid Boons</h4>
<div class="tooltip-spread two-items">
  <a class="wow-spell" data-id="98008"></a>
  <a class="wow-spell" data-id="2825"></a>
</div>

<p>Spirit Link Totem is arguably a raid cooldown, but as I&#39;ve espoused before it can also serve under exceptional circumstances to save numerous lives. Shaman also has a standard raid cooldown already in Healing Tide Totem.</p>
<h4 id="personal-aids">Personal Aids</h4>
<div class="tooltip-spread">
  <a class="wow-spell" data-id="108271"></a>
  <a class="wow-spell" data-id="51514"></a>
  <a class="wow-spell" data-id="370"></a>
</div>

<div class="tooltip-spread two-items">
  <a class="wow-spell" data-id="20608"></a>
  <a class="wow-spell" data-id="57994"></a>
</div>

<h5 id="summary">Summary</h5>
<p>In total Shamans have around 8 base abilities that exist outside of their standard pool of spells, including the only healer interrupt in the game. There are plenty of talents and artifact traits that augment these, leading to arguably the most interesting healing artifact in the game.</p>
<h3 id="talents">Talents</h3>
<h4 id="mobility">Mobility</h4>
<div>
  <a class="wow-spell wide" data-id="192063"></a>
</div>

<h4 id="raid-boons">Raid Boons</h4>
<div class="tooltip-spread">
  <a class="wow-spell" data-id="192077"></a>
  <a class="wow-spell" data-id="192058"></a>
  <a class="wow-spell" data-id="51485"></a>
</div>

<div class="tooltip-spread">
  <a class="wow-spell" data-id="196932"></a>
  <a class="wow-spell" data-id="207399"></a>
  <a class="wow-spell" data-id="207401"></a>
</div>

<h4 id="personal-aids">Personal Aids</h4>
<p>Seemingly none.</p>
<h3 id="artifact">Artifact</h3>
<p>No extra spells or effects, but plenty of augments onto the existing spells we&#39;ve already covered.</p>
<hr>
<h2 id="paladin">Paladin</h2>
<h3 id="base-spells">Base Spells</h3>
<h4 id="mobility">Mobility</h4>
<p>None :(</p>
<h4 id="raid-boons">Raid Boons</h4>
<div class="tooltip-spread">
  <a class="wow-spell" data-id="1022"></a>
  <a class="wow-spell" data-id="1044"></a>
  <a class="wow-spell" data-id="633"></a>
</div>

<p>I&#39;ve considered Aura Mastery, but it doesn&#39;t seem as exceptional as something such as Spirit Link Totem.</p>
<h4 id="personal-aids">Personal Aids</h4>
<div class="tooltip-spread">
  <a class="wow-spell" data-id="642"></a>
  <a class="wow-spell" data-id="853"></a>
  <a class="wow-spell" data-id="498"></a>
</div>

<p>Lay on Hands is definitely arguable, but it does serve the unique purpose of saving a life with a button instantly, and Paladins have an existing tank cooldown in Hand of Sacrifice.</p>
<h5 id="summary">Summary</h5>
<p>Paladins have around 6 base abilities that aren&#39;t in their standard pool, including a very powerful immunity and personal cooldown. They also have a baseline 15% extra EHP regardless of whether or not Aura of Sacrifice is talented or not. Again, plenty of talents and artifact traits augment these abilities.</p>
<h3 id="talents">Talents</h3>
<h4 id="mobility">Mobility</h4>
<div>
  <a class="wow-spell wide" data-id="205656"></a>
</div>

<h4 id="raid-boons">Raid Boons</h4>
<div>
  <a class="wow-spell wide" data-id="115750"></a>
</div>

<h4 id="personal-aids">Personal Aids</h4>
<div>
  <a class="wow-spell wide" data-id="20066"></a>
</div>

<h5 id="summary">Summary</h5>
<p>Not much here, a lot of power is baked into Aura Mastery which may not show through in this, especially when you consider AM increases healing done with artifact traits.</p>
<h3 id="artifact">Artifact</h3>
<h4 id="mobility">Mobility</h4>
<p>Nada.</p>
<h4 id="raid-boons">Raid Boons</h4>
<div>
  <a class="wow-spell wide" data-id="200430"></a>
</div>

<p>Including this because 15% extra healing is a huge amount for a cooldown to have over 8 seconds in addition to the baseline effects that it already includes.</p>
<h4 id="personal-aids">Personal Aids</h4>
<div>
  <a class="wow-spell wide" data-id="200302"></a>
</div>

<p>Essentially makes Judgment a smaller personal cooldown.</p>
<hr>
<h2 id="druid">Druid</h2>
<h3 id="base-spells">Base Spells</h3>
<h4 id="mobility">Mobility</h4>
<div class="tooltip-spread two-items">
  <a class="wow-spell" data-id="783"></a>
  <a class="wow-spell" data-id="1850"></a>
</div>

<h4 id="raid-boons">Raid Boons</h4>
<div class="tooltip-spread">
  <a class="wow-spell" data-id="102793"></a>
  <a class="wow-spell" data-id="29166"></a>
  <a class="wow-spell" data-id="20484"></a>
</div>

<p>Yes Tiberria, Innervate is useful to a raid.</p>
<h4 id="personal-aids">Personal Aids</h4>
<div class="tooltip-spread two-items">
  <a class="wow-spell" data-id="339"></a>
  <a class="wow-spell" data-id="22812"></a>
</div>

<h5 id="summary">Summary</h5>
<p>Druids have around 7 baseline abilities that fulfil the criteria we&#39;ve defined, granted some are maybe not as powerful as other classes (Dash), but none the less they have some very strong effects present here too such as Innervate and Ursol&#39;s Vortex.</p>
<h3 id="talents">Talents</h3>
<h4 id="mobility">Mobility</h4>
<div class="tooltip-spread">
  <a class="wow-spell" data-id="102280"></a>
  <a class="wow-spell" data-id="132302"></a>
  <a class="wow-spell" data-id="197490"></a>
</div>

<h4 id="raid-boons">Raid Boons</h4>
<div class="tooltip-spread two-items">
  <a class="wow-spell" data-id="102359"></a>
  <a class="wow-spell" data-id="132469"></a>
</div>

<h4 id="personal-aids">Personal Aids</h4>
<div class="tooltip-spread">
  <a class="wow-spell" data-id="197491"></a>
  <a class="wow-spell" data-id="5211"></a>
  <a class="wow-spell" data-id="33891"></a>
</div>

<h5 id="summary">Summary</h5>
<p>A varied set of tools are available in the Druid&#39;s talent array to help deal with any situation, possibly the second strongest set of talents behind Shamans.</p>
<h3 id="artifact">Artifact</h3>
<h4 id="mobility">Mobility</h4>
<div>
  <a class="wow-spell wide" data-id="189857"></a>
</div>

<hr>
<h2 id="discipline">Discipline</h2>
<h3 id="base-spells">Base Spells</h3>
<h4 id="mobility">Mobility</h4>
<p>Nada.</p>
<h4 id="raid-boons">Raid Boons</h4>
<div class="tooltip-spread">
  <a class="wow-spell" data-id="8122"></a>
  <a class="wow-spell" data-id="81749"></a>
  <a class="wow-spell" data-id="528"></a>
</div>

<div class="tooltip-spread">
  <a class="wow-spell" data-id="605"></a>
  <a class="wow-spell" data-id="32375"></a>
  <a class="wow-spell" data-id="73325"></a>
</div>

<h4 id="personal-aids">Personal Aids</h4>
<div class="tooltip-spread two-items">
  <a class="wow-spell" data-id="586"></a>
</div>

<h5 id="summary">Summary</h5>
<p>Again around 7 extra abilities, with a few of them being extremely powerful in past content and unlikely to diminish in future. We&#39;re talking about things such as Mass Dispel and Lifegrip here.</p>
<h3 id="talents">Talents</h3>
<h4 id="mobility">Mobility</h4>
<div class="tooltip-spread two-items">
  <a class="wow-spell" data-id="121536"></a>
  <a class="wow-spell" data-id="64129"></a>
</div>

<h4 id="raid-boons">Raid Boons</h4>
<div>
  <a class="wow-spell wide" data-id="204263"></a>
</div>

<h4 id="personal-aids">Personal Aids</h4>
<div>
  <a class="wow-spell wide" data-id="10060"></a>
</div>

<h5 id="summary">Summary</h5>
<p>Not as much unique abilities in Discipline&#39;s talents, but a lot of it compounds upon Atonement.</p>
<h3 id="artifact">Artifact</h3>
<h4 id="mobility">Mobility</h4>
<div>
  <a class="wow-spell wide" data-id="197766"></a>
</div>

<h4 id="raid-boons">Raid Boons</h4>
<p>None.</p>
<h4 id="personal-aids">Personal Aids</h4>
<div>
  <a class="wow-spell wide" data-id="197781"></a>
</div>

<h5 id="summary">Summary</h5>
<p>Again not a huge amount of stuff in Discipline&#39;s artifact that doesn&#39;t build on the existing Atonement mechanic.</p>
<hr>
<h2 id="holy-priest">Holy Priest</h2>
<h3 id="base-spells">Base Spells</h3>
<h4 id="mobility">Mobility</h4>
<p>Nada.</p>
<h4 id="raid-boons">Raid Boons</h4>
<div class="tooltip-spread">
  <a class="wow-spell" data-id="528"></a>
  <a class="wow-spell" data-id="32375"></a>
  <a class="wow-spell" data-id="73325"></a>
</div>

<div class="tooltip-spread two-items">
  <a class="wow-spell" data-id="605"></a>
  <a class="wow-spell" data-id="20711"></a>
</div>

<h4 id="personal-aids">Personal Aids</h4>
<div class="tooltip-spread two-items">
  <a class="wow-spell" data-id="586"></a>
  <a class="wow-spell" data-id="88625"></a>
</div>

<h5 id="summary">Summary</h5>
<p>Once again 7 abilities, some overlap with Discipline but that is to be expected when you share a base class.</p>
<h3 id="talents">Talents</h3>
<h4 id="mobility">Mobility</h4>
<div class="tooltip-spread two-items">
  <a class="wow-spell" data-id="121536"></a>
  <a class="wow-spell" data-id="214121"></a>
</div>

<h4 id="raid-boons">Raid Boons</h4>
<div class="tooltip-spread two-items">
  <a class="wow-spell" data-id="204263"></a>
  <a class="wow-spell" data-id="64901"></a>
</div>

<h4 id="personal-aids">Personal Aids</h4>
<p>None.</p>
<h5 id="summary">Summary</h5>
<p>Not as much unique abilities in Discipline&#39;s talents, but a lot of it compounds upon Atonement.</p>
<h3 id="artifact">Artifact</h3>
<h4 id="mobility">Mobility</h4>
<div>
  <a class="wow-spell wide" data-id="196419"></a>
</div>

<h4 id="raid-boons">Raid Boons</h4>
<p>None.</p>
<h4 id="personal-aids">Personal Aids</h4>
<p>None.</p>
<h5 id="summary">Summary</h5>
<p>Only one significant effect here, and it&#39;s more of an enhancement than a unique ability.</p>
<hr>
<h2 id="mistweaver">Mistweaver</h2>
<h3 id="base-spells">Base Spells</h3>
<h4 id="mobility">Mobility</h4>
<div class="tooltip-spread two-items">
  <a class="wow-spell" data-id="109132"></a>
  <a class="wow-spell" data-id="119996"></a>
</div>

<h4 id="raid-boons">Raid Boons</h4>
<p>Nada.</p>
<h4 id="personal-aids">Personal Aids</h4>
<div>
  <a class="wow-spell wide" data-id="115078"></a>
</div>

<h5 id="summary">Summary</h5>
<p>The outlier of the bunch in terms of base abilities, there is such a huge margin, the next runner ups have at least 7 abilities. You&#39;re counting right, Mistweaver has 3.</p>
<h3 id="talents">Talents</h3>
<h4 id="mobility">Mobility</h4>
<div class="tooltip-spread two-items">
  <a class="wow-spell" data-id="116841"></a>
  <a class="wow-spell" data-id="197945"></a>
</div>

<h4 id="raid-boons">Raid Boons</h4>
<div class="tooltip-spread">
  <a class="wow-spell" data-id="116844"></a>
  <a class="wow-spell" data-id="198898"></a>
  <a class="wow-spell" data-id="119381"></a>
</div>

<div>
  <a class="wow-spell wide" data-id="210804"></a>
</div>

<h4 id="personal-aids">Personal Aids</h4>
<div class="tooltip-spread">
  <a class="wow-spell" data-id="122280"></a>
  <a class="wow-spell" data-id="122783"></a>
  <a class="wow-spell" data-id="122278"></a>
</div>

<h5 id="summary">Summary</h5>
<p>A solid 5 abilities, Mistweavers will likely pick up Leg Sweep as both Ring of Peace and Song of Chi-Ji are particularly bad. The latter is probably one of the worst talents in this entire review. They can also pick up their defensive cooldown here, but are relegated to either Diffuse Magic or a poor incarnation of Dampen Harm balanced around tank damage income.</p>
<h3 id="artifact">Artifact</h3>
<h4 id="mobility">Mobility</h4>
<div>
  <a class="wow-spell wide" data-id="199401"></a>
</div>

<h4 id="raid-boons">Raid Boons</h4>
<div>
  <a class="wow-spell wide" data-id="199384"></a>
</div>

<h4 id="personal-aids">Personal Aids</h4>
<p>None.</p>
<h5 id="summary">Summary</h5>
<p>Again not very significant effects, Light on Your Feet being an exceptional example of how to disappoint.</p>
<hr>
<h2 id="tally">Tally</h2>
<h3 id="base">Base</h3>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Resto Shaman</th>
<th>Holy Paladin</th>
<th>Resto Druid</th>
<th>Discipline Priest</th>
<th>Holy Priest</th>
<th>Mistweaver</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>8</td>
<td>7</td>
<td>7</td>
<td>7</td>
<td>7</td>
<td>3</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<h3 id="talent">Talent</h3>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Resto Shaman</th>
<th>Holy Paladin</th>
<th>Resto Druid</th>
<th>Discipline Priest</th>
<th>Holy Priest</th>
<th>Mistweaver</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>7</td>
<td>3</td>
<td>8</td>
<td>4</td>
<td>4</td>
<td>5</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<h3 id="artifact">Artifact</h3>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Resto Shaman</th>
<th>Holy Paladin</th>
<th>Resto Druid</th>
<th>Discipline Priest</th>
<th>Holy Priest</th>
<th>Mistweaver</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>0</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>2</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<h3 id="total">Total</h3>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Resto Shaman</th>
<th>Holy Paladin</th>
<th>Resto Druid</th>
<th>Discipline Priest</th>
<th>Holy Priest</th>
<th>Mistweaver</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>15</td>
<td>12</td>
<td>16</td>
<td>13</td>
<td>12</td>
<td>10</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<h2 id="the-zero-sum-game">The Zero Sum Game</h2>
<p>There isn&#39;t a zero sum game, obviously World of Warcraft has a little more nuance than adding up ability numbers and declaring the lowest the worst. However I&#39;d ask you to go look at the quality of an Artifact such as the Resto Shamans and compare it to a Mistweaver. Here&#39;s an example of two traits taken from similar locations in each weapon:</p>
<div class="tooltip-spread two-items">
  <a class="wow-spell" data-id="207356"></a>
  <a class="wow-spell" data-id="199364"></a>
</div>

<p>Obviously this is somewhat cherry picked, but if you look at the amount of plain static % increases to commonly used abilities in the Mistweaver artifact and compare it to the amount that exist in the Shaman artifact, you can clearly see that the extra design space afforded by more base abilities is being taken advantage of. Ultimately it&#39;s resulting in a far more fun looking set of traits, which tie shamans together in a way that the highly atomic kit of a Mistweaver just hasn&#39;t been able to benefit from.</p>
<p>We can see players already shunning spells like Essence Font because it just has no real interactions with anything else, it&#39;s not building on a legacy spell like Spinning Crane Kick or adding anything new and exciting. There are no artifact traits that build a spell like Essence Font into something better and more interesting, and as a result abilities like Rising Thunder which bring radical gameplay changes on the back of a legacy playstyle players are more aware of are proving to be better than the base spec itself.</p>
<p>The developers need to realize that if they want the emotional effect from Artifacts to be successful, and if they want the new Mistweaver to be enjoyable, they need to stop adding 5% buffs and mobility effects that are severely diminished by our already strong mobility. What we need to see is more base abilities, more artifact traits that hinge off these base abilities, and more talents which pivot off them to provide gameplay changes that are meaningful in the likes of Rising Thunder.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Thanks to mserrano and Renray for proof reading my potato writing.</p>
</blockquote>
]]></description><link>http://bestmonk.xyz/blog/mistweaver-design-space</link><guid isPermaLink="true">http://bestmonk.xyz/blog/mistweaver-design-space</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Reglitch]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 14 Mar 2016 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Item Level Budgeting Changes]]></title><description><![CDATA[<h2 id="secondaries-are-still-good">Secondaries Are Still Good</h2>
<p>The developers have recently announced a change to secondary stats in Legion, what this means for the typical player is that you&#39;ll spend a lot more of the expansion with a level of stats that feels better. If you have played a previous expansion, there is always a small period of time when all players have very small amounts of stats and feel significantly weaker than they were even at the last level cap.</p>
<p>You can look through the post <a href="http://us.battle.net/wow/en/forum/topic/20742704730?page=1#1">here</a>, but for the purposes of this post all you need to really see is the following:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Conversion rates of Rating-&gt;% for secondary stats will not go up as much as they otherwise would, by a huge margin. The conversion rates will end up at 110 at less than half of what they otherwise would have, resulting in Legion dungeon blue gear providing over double the total secondary stat %s, as the it did in prior expansions.</p>
<p>Starting at ilvl 800, the exponential curve for secondary stats will be significantly reduced, nearly to being linear (this is per-item, not related to the character&#39;s average item level). Primary stats and Stamina will continue to scale exponentially with ilvl at the same rate as before. This will mean that players retain all of the same customization they had, but with secondary stat %s not scaling higher than they had before, by the end of the expansion.</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<h3 id="how-does-this-effect-stat-scaling">How Does This Effect Stat Scaling</h3>
<p>This change alone does not, however the scalars for all secondaries has been changed with this build. The usual diminishment on stats per point as you level will not be as radical also. What this means is that at level 110, one point of each stat will give you significantly <em>more</em> than it did before.</p>
<pre><code class="hljs"><span class="hljs-prompt">Haste: 445 -&gt;</span> <span class="hljs-number">275</span>
<span class="hljs-prompt">Crit: 490 -&gt;</span> <span class="hljs-number">300</span>
<span class="hljs-prompt">Mastery: 490 -&gt;</span> <span class="hljs-number">300</span>
<span class="hljs-prompt">Versatility: 590 -&gt;</span> <span class="hljs-number">350</span></code></pre>


<p>You get almost double of what you otherwise would have from each point of stats in the current build. Interestingly, primary stat scaling remains as it has always been, but with secondary statistics giving double the amount they used to a lot of classes may start preferring them over their primary statistic. This is unlikely to last though.</p>
<hr>
<h3 id="what-does-this-mean-for-items-">What Does This Mean for Items?</h3>
<p>For items this means that the increase of secondary statistics will be offset by an internal value, resulting in a much more linear increase. This ultimately results in less secondary stats, but they are more powerful to offset for that.</p>
<p>To add to that, the current method of improving artifacts relies on socketing relics that improve your item level. If you&#39;re interested in what those increases look like you can make use of the <a href="/item-calculator">Item Calculator</a> for Legion. It will recursively calculate the changes of stats from one item level to another between the range that is effected by these changes. It will also give you information of how much of a % change the result is, so you can better gauge the strength of each increase.</p>
<hr>
<h3 id="what-does-this-mean-for-me-">What Does This Mean for Me?</h3>
<p>Probably nothing, outside of seriously strong secondaries there is nothing of interest in these changes. Your predicted strongest stat is likely the same (ceteris paribus), and with the removal of spirit these changes really don&#39;t have much of an impact on healer gameplay. There may be minor interesting ways with how these changes interact with procs on trinkets and so on, but those remain to be seen!</p>
]]></description><link>http://bestmonk.xyz/blog/item-level-budgeting-changes</link><guid isPermaLink="true">http://bestmonk.xyz/blog/item-level-budgeting-changes</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Reglitch]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 03 Mar 2016 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Rising Thunder]]></title><description><![CDATA[<h2 id="fistweaving-with-feeling">Fistweaving, With Feeling</h2>
<p>One of the most common criticisms with the Mistweaver specialization in Legion is that Fistweaving was seemingly deleted. With <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/wow/comments/3pa6ra/spec_diversity_legionunofficial_leak/">early leaks</a> speculating that Mistweavers would be doing lots of complaining, this was something I personally had expected for a while, but not to the extent where Mistweavers would be delegated to the range stack. Extremely disappointing, but nothing new when it comes to choices with the Mistweaver.</p>
<p>With the latest build however, we have two new talents that bring us back into melee with a gameplay that mimics the old times of Throne of Thunder. Let&#39;s take a look.</p>
<hr>
<h3 id="the-holy-trinity">The Holy Trinity</h3>
<div class="tooltip-spread">
  <a class="wow-spell" data-id="210802"></a>
  <a class="wow-spell" data-id="116645"></a>
  <a class="wow-spell" data-id="210804"></a>
</div>

<hr>
<p>In Warlords, Fistweaving has been gated behind a stance, and the spec was given a 1.5 second GCD along with more cast times. This has been successful in wiping out any &#39;cherry picking&#39; that was present in the spec, but entirely destroyed the original feel of slamming your enemies with a punch or two between throwing out instant heals. On top of this, the stance was implemented quite poorly, with an on GCD switch that took too long to switch in to. This definitely made you commit into Crane stance a lot more, but oftentimes it fell by the wayside for players who weren&#39;t confident or didn&#39;t feel like the effort was worth it.</p>
<p>This is the return of the original playstyle, but more in thanks to Rising Thunder than Spirit of the Crane. With these talents paying attention to enemies and your full kit is rewarded, maybe not as much as it could be, but definitely more than what have been seeing with Legion so far. Eminence might be gone, but thanks to the synergy between Gust of Mist, Renewing Mist, Thunder Focus Tea, and Rising Thunder, finding an enemy and punching them in the face has never been a better idea.</p>
<hr>
<h3 id="damage-for-healers">Damage for Healers</h3>
<p>Damage is an important thing in World of Warcraft, it is arguably the primary driver for the majority of changes in game state. Plans are currently to have healers level through content in their healing specialization due to Artifacts. Now more than ever, Healers should be concerned about their ability to deal damage while also having fun.</p>
<p>I might have lost some people there, there is definitely a case to be made for healers who rolled healers to heal - period. I also think there&#39;s some validity in the minds of damage dealers who worry their role will be outmoded. Luckily there are a couple of solutions for these worries:</p>
<ul>
<li>The option to opt-out of traditional methods of dealing damage, and further emphasize the support role to provide similar contributions.</li>
<li>The current damage buff on PTR for certain healing classes in open world situations.</li>
</ul>
<p>To be completely clear, <strong>I am not advocating for the buffing of healer damage to be close with dps.</strong> Instead I am advocating that healer damage should be useful in a few <em>very specific</em> contexts:</p>
<ul>
<li>When a skilled (team of) healer(s) have significantly outplayed or outgeared content, allowing them to provide contributions past the binary measure of success of keeping players alive.</li>
<li>When a healer is alone and has to kill an enemy to meet basic requirements in the game such as quests or daily quests.</li>
<li>When damage is valued so much that even providing a small amount more is more valuable than maintaining full healing output. (Burst)</li>
</ul>
<p>Ultimately Rising Thunder brings this to the table, it provides an easy way of contributing damage and thus if you improve your play with Rising Thunder you will see success past simply keeping people alive - you will also see more damage. Point #2 could be improved upon, Rising Thunder does not significantly effect your playstyle while alone, but a damage effect could be quite easily added to TFT&#39;s buff pool. I would suggest something along these lines:</p>
<div>
  <a class="wow-spell wide" data-id="116680"></a>
</div>

<p>Slap on a Blackout Kick cleave and a huge buff to TP damage in memoriam. Not only would it significantly improve Mistweaver damage while solo, it would also provide a higher skill cap for skilled players who cannot further improve their healing in the circumstances.</p>
<hr>
<h3 id="so-what-does-rising-thunder-do">So What does Rising Thunder Do</h3>
<p>Simply put; Rising Thunder puts your Thunder Focus Tea on a much shorter cooldown and allows it to scale with haste. This has interesting effects particularly for Renewing Mist. For example, without Rising Thunder haste will increase your Renewing Mist healing by the amount of haste you have, say 30% haste will mean exactly 30% more raw Renewing Mist healing.</p>
<p class="stretch"><a href="/images/abilityfreq.png"><img src="/images/abilityfreq.png" alt="Holy Shit"></a></p>

<p>As you can see, the amount of <em>everything</em> scales up with haste pretty much directly. These numbers are taken from the output of a simulation, with a rotation of,</p>
<blockquote>
<p>TFT off CD -&gt; ReM with TFT Stacks -&gt; RSK off CD -&gt; ReM without TFT stacks -&gt; TP</p>
</blockquote>
<p>In the event that you spend your TFT on Renewing Mist exclusively, you get an appropriate amount of more ReM casts considering your haste level. Haste also benefits these additional Renewing Mist instances, while this doesn&#39;t create an effect such as Armor Penetration where getting more made the stat better, it does mean that the stat is <em>significantly</em> better than anything else for doing this one specific thing. So much so I believe that it has the potential to drive stat priorities significantly towards haste and mastery.</p>
<hr>
<h3 id="in-summary">In Summary</h3>
<p>Rising Thunder and Spirit of the Crane are two very needed talents in the healer meta and the game needs to see more of them. Statements such as,</p>
<blockquote>
<p>For Mistweavers, it’s OK to have open global cooldowns between heals—Soothing Mist fills these gaps.</p>
</blockquote>
<p><a href="http://us.battle.net/wow/en/blog/19964703/legion-class-preview-series-monk-11-11-2015">http://us.battle.net/wow/en/blog/19964703/legion-class-preview-series-monk-11-11-2015</a></p>
<p>Are very uninspiring, especially for a specialization such as the Mistweaver which has a very strong history in being incredibly active. It&#39;s not okay to have open global cooldowns in an environment where individuals are extremely competitive. Players should never be left in a situation where improving their performance meaningfully is impossible.</p>
<p>As I said at the beginning of this post, these additions are a start, Mistweavers in particular have a lot of snap decision potential to regain after losing both their interrupt and Touch of Death. These abilities contribute a huge amount to the skill cap of the spec, interrupting for example has historically been one of the things that made a great healer great.</p>
<p>This has been my first effort post in ~2.5 years or so, I think it&#39;s not entirely crap. Poking around and figuring out how these abilities will shape the experience for Mistweavers going forward has been fun, now we just need to stop Blizzard deleting them in the next build.</p>
<p>Remember to click the footer! ( ͡° ͜ʖ ͡°)</p>
]]></description><link>http://bestmonk.xyz/blog/rising-thunder</link><guid isPermaLink="true">http://bestmonk.xyz/blog/rising-thunder</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Reglitch]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 12 Feb 2016 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>