<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title><![CDATA[Best Monk]]></title><description><![CDATA[Best Monk]]></description><link>http://bestmonk.xyz</link><generator>metalsmith-feed</generator><lastBuildDate>Thu, 03 Mar 2016 18:30:36 GMT</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://bestmonk.xyz/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title><![CDATA[Item Level Budgeting Changes]]></title><description><![CDATA[<h2 id="secondaries-are-still-good">Secondaries Are Still Good</h2>
<p>The developers have recently announced a change to secondary stats in Legion, what this means for the typical player is that you&#39;ll spend a lot more of the expansion with a level of stats that feels better. If you have played a previous expansion, there is always a small period of time when all players have very small amounts of stats and feel significantly weaker than they were even at the last level cap.</p>
<p>You can look through the post <a href="http://us.battle.net/wow/en/forum/topic/20742704730?page=1#1">here</a>, but for the purposes of this post all you need to really see is the following:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Conversion rates of Rating-&gt;% for secondary stats will not go up as much as they otherwise would, by a huge margin. The conversion rates will end up at 110 at less than half of what they otherwise would have, resulting in Legion dungeon blue gear providing over double the total secondary stat %s, as the it did in prior expansions.</p>
<p>Starting at ilvl 800, the exponential curve for secondary stats will be significantly reduced, nearly to being linear (this is per-item, not related to the character&#39;s average item level). Primary stats and Stamina will continue to scale exponentially with ilvl at the same rate as before. This will mean that players retain all of the same customization they had, but with secondary stat %s not scaling higher than they had before, by the end of the expansion.</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<h3 id="how-does-this-effect-stat-scaling">How Does This Effect Stat Scaling</h3>
<p>This change alone does not, however the scalars for all secondaries has been changed with this build. The usual diminishment on stats per point as you level will not be as radical also. What this means is that at level 110, one point of each stat will give you significantly <em>more</em> than it did before.</p>
<pre><code class="hljs"><span class="hljs-prompt">Haste: 445 -&gt;</span> <span class="hljs-number">227</span>
<span class="hljs-prompt">Crit: 490 -&gt;</span> <span class="hljs-number">250</span>
<span class="hljs-prompt">Mastery: 490 -&gt;</span> <span class="hljs-number">250</span>
<span class="hljs-prompt">Versatility: 590 -&gt;</span> <span class="hljs-number">295</span></code></pre>


<p>You get almost double of what you otherwise would have from each point of stats in the current build. Interestingly, primary stat scaling remains as it has always been, but with secondary statistics giving double the amount they used to a lot of classes may start preferring them over their primary statistic. This is unlikely to last though.</p>
<hr>
<h3 id="what-does-this-mean-for-items-">What Does This Mean for Items?</h3>
<p>For items this means that the increase of secondary statistics will be offset by an internal value, resulting in a much more linear increase. This ultimately results in less secondary stats, but they are more powerful to offset for that.</p>
<p>To add to that, the current method of improving artifacts relies on socketing relics that improve your item level. If you&#39;re interested in what those increases look like you can make use of the <a href="/item-calculator">Item Calculator</a> for Legion. It will recursively calculate the changes of stats from one item level to another between the range that is effected by these changes. It will also give you information of how much of a % change the result is, so you can better gauge the strength of each increase.</p>
<hr>
<h3 id="what-does-this-mean-for-me-">What Does This Mean for Me?</h3>
<p>Probably nothing, outside of seriously strong secondaries there is nothing of interest in these changes. Your predicted strongest stat is likely the same (ceteris paribus), and with the removal of spirit these changes really don&#39;t have much of an impact on healer gameplay. There may be minor interesting ways with how these changes interact with procs on trinkets and so on, but those remain to be seen!</p>
]]></description><link>http://bestmonk.xyz/blog/item-level-budgeting-changes</link><guid isPermaLink="true">http://bestmonk.xyz/blog/item-level-budgeting-changes</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Reglitch]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 03 Mar 2016 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Rising Thunder]]></title><description><![CDATA[<h2 id="fistweaving-with-feeling">Fistweaving, With Feeling</h2>
<p>One of the most common criticisms with the Mistweaver specialization in Legion is that Fistweaving was seemingly deleted. With <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/wow/comments/3pa6ra/spec_diversity_legionunofficial_leak/">early leaks</a> speculating that Mistweavers would be doing lots of complaining, this was something I personally had expected for a while, but not to the extent where Mistweavers would be delegated to the range stack. Extremely disappointing, but nothing new when it comes to choices with the Mistweaver.</p>
<p>With the latest build however, we have two new talents that bring us back into melee with a gameplay that mimics the old times of Throne of Thunder. Let&#39;s take a look.</p>
<hr>
<h3 id="the-holy-trinity">The Holy Trinity</h3>
<div class="tooltip-spread">
  <a class="wow-spell" data-id="210802"></a>
  <a class="wow-spell" data-id="116645"></a>
  <a class="wow-spell" data-id="210804"></a>
</div>

<hr>
<p>In Warlords, Fistweaving has been gated behind a stance, and the spec was given a 1.5 second GCD along with more cast times. This has been successful in wiping out any &#39;cherry picking&#39; that was present in the spec, but entirely destroyed the original feel of slamming your enemies with a punch or two between throwing out instant heals. On top of this, the stance was implemented quite poorly, with an on GCD switch that took too long to switch in to. This definitely made you commit into Crane stance a lot more, but oftentimes it fell by the wayside for players who weren&#39;t confident or didn&#39;t feel like the effort was worth it.</p>
<p>This is the return of the original playstyle, but more in thanks to Rising Thunder than Spirit of the Crane. With these talents paying attention to enemies and your full kit is rewarded, maybe not as much as it could be, but definitely more than what have been seeing with Legion so far. Eminence might be gone, but thanks to the synergy between Gust of Mist, Renewing Mist, Thunder Focus Tea, and Rising Thunder, finding an enemy and punching them in the face has never been a better idea.</p>
<hr>
<h3 id="damage-for-healers">Damage for Healers</h3>
<p>Damage is an important thing in World of Warcraft, it is arguably the primary driver for the majority of changes in game state. Plans are currently to have healers level through content in their healing specialization due to Artifacts. Now more than ever, Healers should be concerned about their ability to deal damage while also having fun.</p>
<p>I might have lost some people there, there is definitely a case to be made for healers who rolled healers to heal - period. I also think there&#39;s some validity in the minds of damage dealers who worry their role will be outmoded. Luckily there are a couple of solutions for these worries:</p>
<ul>
<li>The option to opt-out of traditional methods of dealing damage, and further emphasize the support role to provide similar contributions.</li>
<li>The current damage buff on PTR for certain healing classes in open world situations.</li>
</ul>
<p>To be completely clear, <strong>I am not advocating for the buffing of healer damage to be close with dps.</strong> Instead I am advocating that healer damage should be useful in a few <em>very specific</em> contexts:</p>
<ul>
<li>When a skilled (team of) healer(s) have significantly outplayed or outgeared content, allowing them to provide contributions past the binary measure of success of keeping players alive.</li>
<li>When a healer is alone and has to kill an enemy to meet basic requirements in the game such as quests or daily quests.</li>
<li>When damage is valued so much that even providing a small amount more is more valuable than maintaining full healing output. (Burst)</li>
</ul>
<p>Ultimately Rising Thunder brings this to the table, it provides an easy way of contributing damage and thus if you improve your play with Rising Thunder you will see success past simply keeping people alive - you will also see more damage. Point #2 could be improved upon, Rising Thunder does not significantly effect your playstyle while alone, but a damage effect could be quite easily added to TFT&#39;s buff pool. I would suggest something along these lines:</p>
<div>
  <a class="wow-spell wide" data-id="116680"></a>
</div>

<p>Slap on a Blackout Kick cleave and a huge buff to TP damage in memoriam. Not only would it significantly improve Mistweaver damage while solo, it would also provide a higher skill cap for skilled players who cannot further improve their healing in the circumstances.</p>
<hr>
<h3 id="so-what-does-rising-thunder-do">So What does Rising Thunder Do</h3>
<p>Simply put; Rising Thunder puts your Thunder Focus Tea on a much shorter cooldown and allows it to scale with haste. This has interesting effects particularly for Renewing Mist. For example, without Rising Thunder haste will increase your Renewing Mist healing by the amount of haste you have, say 30% haste will mean exactly 30% more raw Renewing Mist healing.</p>
<p class="stretch"><a href="/images/abilityfreq.png"><img src="/images/abilityfreq.png" alt="Holy Shit"></a></p>

<p>As you can see, the amount of <em>everything</em> scales up with haste pretty much directly. These numbers are taken from the output of a simulation, with a rotation of,</p>
<blockquote>
<p>TFT off CD -&gt; ReM with TFT Stacks -&gt; RSK off CD -&gt; ReM without TFT stacks -&gt; TP</p>
</blockquote>
<p>In the event that you spend your TFT on Renewing Mist exclusively, you get an appropriate amount of more ReM casts considering your haste level. Haste also benefits these additional Renewing Mist instances, while this doesn&#39;t create an effect such as Armor Penetration where getting more made the stat better, it does mean that the stat is <em>significantly</em> better than anything else for doing this one specific thing. So much so I believe that it has the potential to drive stat priorities significantly towards haste and mastery.</p>
<hr>
<h3 id="in-summary">In Summary</h3>
<p>Rising Thunder and Spirit of the Crane are two very needed talents in the healer meta and the game needs to see more of them. Statements such as,</p>
<blockquote>
<p>For Mistweavers, it’s OK to have open global cooldowns between heals—Soothing Mist fills these gaps.</p>
</blockquote>
<p><a href="http://us.battle.net/wow/en/blog/19964703/legion-class-preview-series-monk-11-11-2015">http://us.battle.net/wow/en/blog/19964703/legion-class-preview-series-monk-11-11-2015</a></p>
<p>Are very uninspiring, especially for a specialization such as the Mistweaver which has a very strong history in being incredibly active. It&#39;s not okay to have open global cooldowns in an environment where individuals are extremely competitive. Players should never be left in a situation where improving their performance meaningfully is impossible.</p>
<p>As I said at the beginning of this post, these additions are a start, Mistweavers in particular have a lot of snap decision potential to regain after losing both their interrupt and Touch of Death. These abilities contribute a huge amount to the skill cap of the spec, interrupting for example has historically been one of the things that made a great healer great.</p>
<p>This has been my first effort post in ~2.5 years or so, I think it&#39;s not entirely crap. Poking around and figuring out how these abilities will shape the experience for Mistweavers going forward has been fun, now we just need to stop Blizzard deleting them in the next build.</p>
<p>Remember to click the footer! ( ͡° ͜ʖ ͡°)</p>
]]></description><link>http://bestmonk.xyz/blog/rising-thunder</link><guid isPermaLink="true">http://bestmonk.xyz/blog/rising-thunder</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Reglitch]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 12 Feb 2016 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>